<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The dyenge creature]</title>
            <title>Here begynneth a lytell treatyse of the dyenge creature.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1507</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124062</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900549</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900549</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173512</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73775)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173512)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 604:5b, 2060:5b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The dyenge creature]</title>
                  <title>Here begynneth a lytell treatyse of the dyenge creature.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>+[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>in Fletestrete at the sygne of ye sonne, by Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno d[omi]ni. M.CCCCC.vii. [1507]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Title from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: B⁶ C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Copy at reel 2060 bound and filmed following STC 6033.5.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ Here begynneth a lytell treatyſe of the dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>enge creature enfected with ſykenes vncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable with many ſorowfull complayntes.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>Labores <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </q>
                  <q>O homo auerte ab inpatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia animam tuam.</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:4"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>Confuſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mꝰ</q>
                  <q>Heu infame.</q>
                  <q>Futore conſumor</q>
                  <q>Animam amiſimus</q>
                  <q>Spes nobis nulle</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:4"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Làs thàt euer I ſynned in my lyfe to me is come this day y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dredfull tydynges that euer I herde / here hath ben with me a ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geaunt of armes whoſe name is crewelte from the kynge of all kynges / lorde of all lordes / &amp; Iuge of all Iuges lyenge on me his mace of his offyce ſayenge vnto me I areſt you &amp; warne you to make you redy &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye fayle not to be redy euery houre whan ye be called on / ye ſhall not wete whan. And call ſadly to your remembraunce your olde &amp; longe conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued offences / the goodnes of god how largly he hath departed with you the gyftes of nature / the gyftes of fortune &amp; the gyftes of grace / &amp; how he hath departed with you largely &amp; ordeyned you at your baptym thre ſad borowes that ye ſholde ſafly &amp; ſewerly be kepte in your tender age as well from vices as fro bodely pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll &amp; ordeyned you a good aungell to kepe you and to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyll you yf ye haue be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeylled by hym bethynke you. And whan ye come to the yere of dyſcrecyon he or deyned you thre ſad counſeyllers / reaſon / drede / and conſcyence yf ye haue be rewled by theyr cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyll call that to your remembraunce. He ordeyned you alſo. v. wyttes / ſeruauntes that ye ſholde be mayſter of &amp; rule them after your dyſcrecyon / that is to ſaye your felyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / your ſyght / your herynge / your ſpeche / &amp; your taſt How haue ye rewled theſe that be vnder your obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce me thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth ye haue moche thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to anſwere for for the Iuge that ſhall ſytte vpon you he wyll not be percyall nor he wyll not be corrupte with good but he wyll my<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter to you Iuſtyce &amp; equyte certaynly as well as this There were certayne thynges he forbad you &amp; the thynges ye ſholde flee in ony wyſe that is to wete
<pb facs="tcp:173512:5"/> the ſeuen deedly ſynnes and all thynges that ſholde prouoke moue or ſtere you therto he badde you flee / haue ye do ſo / haue ye kepte his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements. x. And yet that is but lytell thynge.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The lamentacyon of the dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>ALas alas exſcuſe me I can not / and whome I myght deſyre to ſpeke for me I wote not / the day &amp; tyme is ſo dredful / the Iuge is ſo ryghtfull myn enmyes be cruell my kyn my neyghbours my frendes my ſeruauntes be not fauourable to me / &amp; alſo I wote well they ſhall not be herde there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The complaynt of the dyenge creature to the good aungell.</head>
               <p>O My good aungell to whome our lorde toke me to kepe where be ye now me thynketh ye ſholde be here now &amp; anſwere for me for the drede of deth dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroubleth me ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can not anſwere for my ſelfe here is my bad aungell redy &amp; is one of my chefe accuſers with legions of fendes with hym &amp; I haue no creature to anſwere for me / alas it is an heuy caas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The anſwere of the good aungell to the dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>AS to your badde dedes I was neuer conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge. I ſawe your natural inclynacyon more dyſpoſed to be rewled by your bad aungell than by me how be it ye can not exſcuſe you but whan ye were pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed
<pb facs="tcp:173512:5"/> to do ony thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes of god I fayled not to remembre you that it was not well &amp; counſeylled you to flee the places of peryll and the company that ſholde ſtere or moue you therto can ye ſaye nay hereto / how can ye thynke that I coude anſwere for you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The complaynt of the dyenge creature to reaſon drede and conſcyence.</head>
               <p>OYe reaſon drede &amp; conſcyence ye were aſſygned to be of my counſeyll now come I requyre you &amp; helpe me to anſwere for me for my defautes be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; ſo abhomynable in the ſyght of hym that ſhall be my Iuge and my accuſers be ſo many &amp; ſo vnfrendly that they leue not one defaute behynde. Now come I require you &amp; helpe to anſwere for me for it was neuer ſo grete nede. The fere &amp; the drede that I am in dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troubleth me ſo that one worde I can not ſpeke for my ſelfe. Alas that euer I ſawe this daye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The anſwere of reaſon.</head>
               <p>BE ye remembred that our lorde ordeyned you a good aungell &amp; a badde aungell / &amp; he ordeyned you reaſon &amp; dyſcrecyon to knowe the good from the yll &amp; he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded you to do good &amp; leue the euyll / he put you in fre choyſe whether ye wolde do well or euyl ye ought to call to your remembraunce how well god hath done for you &amp; helped you in euery daunger &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryll he wolde haue ben loued dred &amp; ſerued accordy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to the many folde graces &amp; kyndeneſſes that he hath ſhewed vnto you how to anſwere for you I wote not loth I am to accuſe you / &amp; excuſe you I can not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:173512:6"/>
               <head>¶ The complaynt to the dyenge creature to drede ſaynge thus.</head>
               <p>ADrede where be ye is there no helpe and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour with you to ſpeke for me whan I ſhall come to my Iugement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The anſwere of drede.</head>
               <p>NO certaynly for whan ye were ſet in pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; delectacyon of the worlde reaſon put in your mynde that ye dyde not well / &amp; I drede was with you at all tymes and in euery place &amp; fayled not to ſpeke vnto you &amp; to put you in mynde of the ſhame of this worlde and drede of dampnacyon &amp; of the peryll that wolde folowe as well here as elles where reherſynge vnto you the punyſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes that our lorde ordeyned for ſynne ſaynge vnto you. Se ye not how gracyouſly our lorde hath called you from ſynne &amp; wretchednes yf ye wolde vnderſtande it / how hath he longe kepte you in worſhyp eſtate and in proſperyte &amp; coude not knowe the goodnes of god / how hath he chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>yſed you &amp; how ofte by loſſe of your chyldren / loſſe of your kyn and frendes / loſſe of your goodes and loſſe of all tho thynges that ye coude not be pleaſed with &amp; ſet you in the indygnacyon of the grete hyghe &amp; myghty prynce and helpe you out of the daungers &amp; perylles that ye haue ben in at all tymes / &amp; yet haue ye not loued hym dred hym &amp; ſerued hym that in all theſe perylles hath preſerued &amp; kepte you &amp; hath ben ſo gracyous &amp; good lorde to you who ſholde ſpeke for you. I. nay certaynly</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The complaynt of the dyenge creature to conſcyence ſaynge thus.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:173512:6"/>
               <p>ALas conſcyence is there no helpe with you I haue herde ſaye longe ago the worlde was to curſte / but I wolde hope that conſcyence wolde haue compaſſyon of my dyſtreſſe and moche the more that I am frendles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The anſwere of conſcyence to the dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>I Am ſory to accuſe you &amp; excuſe you I can not for conſcyence and drede haue ben but ſeldom from you &amp; called vpon you in euery tyme &amp; place of peryll &amp; bad you flee the occaſyons of ſynne ye myght haue fled at that tyme and wolde not / now ye wolde flee deth &amp; can not / we ſholde ſpeke for you &amp; dare not &amp; though we wolde it auayleth not ye muſt ſorowfully &amp; mekely ſuffre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iugementes that ye haue deſerued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The complaynt of the dyenge creature to the fyue wyttes.</head>
               <p>OYe fyue that were ordeyned deyned to be my ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; vnder myn obeyſaunce &amp; to haue be rewled at all tymes as I wolde haue you / is there no good word that ye may a forde to ſaye for me &amp; recorde my deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge to you &amp; reporte of me how I haue rewled and gouerned you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were take me to kepe rewle &amp; gouerne me thynketh ye ſholde ſaye for me now / who myght ſoo well ſaye for me as ye fyue / ye haue ben with me contynually euer ſyth that I was borne nyght &amp; daye and neuer at no tyme from me thynketh of your kyn deneſſe ye ſholde haue compaſſyon vpon me and ſaye the beſt that ye coude ſaye for me. I haue ben frendly to you and brought you in euery place of pleaſaunce and dyſporte / now ſhe we your ky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>denes agayne to me and ſpeke to fayth and hope for me that they wolde
<pb facs="tcp:173512:7"/> charytably do my meſſage vnto the mooſt gloryous prynce that euer was is or ſhall be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The anſwere of the fyue wyttes.</head>
               <p>CErtaynly we meruayll that ye wolde deſyre vs to ſpeke for you vnderſtandynge theſe worſhip full people haue denyed and refuſed to ſpeke for you your good aungell reaſon drede and conſcyence how ſholde we be herde or what credens wyll be gyuen vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs that haue ben your ſeruauntes and vnder your obeyſaunce and no thynge at all tymes but as ye haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded vs to do call to your remembraunce how ye haue rewled vs fyue ſyght herynge felynge and thought ye haue at all tymes brought vs in places of pleaſaunce &amp; dyſporte &amp; thoughe it were dyſporte &amp; pleaſaunce / for the tyme it is now ſorowe wepynge &amp; wayly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge for your ſake that we can not excuſe you nor no thynge ſaye for you that myght be to your wel or to your eſe for we haue ben preuy &amp; partyners to all that hath ben myſdone in ony wyſe and in euery place and youre offences in euery thynge is in your defaute for and ye had ſadly rewled vs and lyke a ſouerayne ye ſholde haue reſtrayned in vs euery vyce / for we ſholde haue be ruled by you in euery thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / &amp; otherwyſe than ye wolde haue vs do we wolde not do / therfore of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyte your defautes muſt be layd vpon you for we haue do as ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſhold do &amp; obeyed you in euery thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge &amp; dyſobeyed you in no thynge / wherfore of ryght the peryll muſt be yours what eredence wyll ye gyue to vs than / yf we ſholde ſay well of you the people wold ſay that we were fals dyſſymulours &amp; fauourers of ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:173512:7"/>
               <head>¶ The lamentacyon of the dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>ALas there is no creature that I can complayn me to but vtterly refuſeth to ſaye ony thynge that myght be to my comforte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playnt of the dyenge creature to fayth &amp; hope.</head>
               <p>O Holy fayth &amp; hope in you is all my truſt for how greuouſly &amp; how myſcheuouſly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer I offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded god you diſpleaſed I neuer. I haue alway byleued as the chyrche of cryſtendome hath taught me &amp; ſpecy ally is of the mooſt holy incarnacyon I was neuer in thought. I haue byleued in the bleſſyd and mooſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous trynyte fader ſone &amp; holy gooſt. I haue byleued that the ſeconde perſone of the trynyte deſcended in to the boſom of the mooſt gloryous and pure chaſt meke vyrgyn that euer was is or ſhall be &amp; medled his very godhede with her pure chaſt virgynyte &amp; maydenhede and in her boſom was parfytly very god &amp; man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued by the grete myſtery of the holy gooſt without knowlege or company of ony erthly man &amp; ſhe a pure chaſt virgyn flowrynge in virgynyte and by herynge of the holy archaungell Gabryell whiche brought vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to her the mooſt gracyous &amp; good tydynges that euer came to man kynde. Now holy Fayth take with you hope &amp; ye twayne of your perfyte charyte be my aduo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cates in the hyghe courte / and refuſe me not nor dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne me not for myn hortyble and abhominable ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes that I haue done / whiche aſketh vengeaunce in this worlde and dampnacyon eternall without the mercyes of hym whiche is almyghty / What meane
<pb facs="tcp:173512:8"/> mygth I haue therto. I praye you counſeyll me for ye knowe well that my reaſon neuer dyſcorded with the fayth / &amp; as to you Hope I hope all wayes that ye wyll ſaye for me that I haue alwayes hoped to the mercyes of god almyghty and that I ſholde be one of the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſaluacyon and one of tho that ſholde be rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the precyous and bytter paynfull paſſion as other ſynners haue be and certaynly other plee nor re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyſtence I can not make. But and ye twayne wolde be a meane for me to that mooſt gloryous and pure chaſte virgyn that choſen was by one aſſent of all the hole gloryous trynyte to do the mooſt gloryous and worſhypfull acte that euer was done for her chaſtyte her pure virgynyte her mekeneſſe her vertue and her conſtaunce was cauſe that ſhe was choſen by all the hole gloryous trynyte to be doughter mother &amp; ſpouſe to the mooſt gloryous trynyte &amp; that ſhe ſholde bere hym that ſholde redeme all mankynde from dampna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon who may ſo well be aduocatryſe to the fader the ſone and the holy gooſt as ſhe and ye wyll be meane to her ſone for me I hope ſhe wyll not refuſe me / for I vnderſtande and knowe well that ſhe hath holpe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a ſynner that hath ryght greuouſly offended and in the holy pſalme that was made bytwene her &amp; her coſyn ſaynt Elyzabeth it was ſayd that all generacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons ſholde blyſſe her. I hope at the begynnynge of the worlde our lorde put not me out of his nombre of tho that ſholde blyſſe his mooſt holy moder &amp; recorde her mercy pyte &amp; grace that ſhe ſhewed to ſynners whan they haue none other ſocour ne helpe. She is moder of orphans / and ſhe is conſolacyon of them that ben dyſſolate / ſhe is guyde to all tho that be out of the way
<pb facs="tcp:173512:8"/> to ſet them in the ryght waye. I am an orphan I am dyſſolate. I am out of the waye I wote not where to crye and call after ſocour and helpe but onely to her that bare our redemptour who may ſo well be meane to the ſone as the moder. And ye twayne Fayth and Hope wolde be meane to the moder of mercy for me. Now gracyous Fayth and Hope do your parte and dyſdayne not my requeſt thoughe I deſyre you to this occuparyon / for and ye twayne wolde denye to ſaye for me I thynke I ſhall fall in dyſpayre for on whome to call after ſocour I wote not / and to put my ſelfe in prees as a poore naked beſt vnclothed of vertue and repleted with vyces naked of grace and in myn owne defaute and to come to the preſence of the kynge of all kynges and vnpouruayed of all thynges that wolde accorde with his mooſt ryall and Imperyall eſtate I dare not take it vpon me I ſholde be in ſuche drede &amp; fere I ſholde not con ne dare not ſpeke for my ſelfe for I haue prayed my good aungell to ſpeke for me and he hath denyed it. I haue called vpon Reaſon Drede and Conſcyens &amp; they haue anſwered me full heuyly that they be loth to accuſe me and exſcuſe me they can not / &amp; alledgeth many a grete reſonable cauſe why y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can not ſaye nay to. I haue called vpon my ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes whiche were take me to rewle and gouerne as I wolde anſwere for them / and they anſwere me ryght ſorowfully &amp; ſaye yf they ſholde ſaye ony good worde for me they ſholde not ſaye trouth of me &amp; caſteth to me that peryll that no body wolde gyue credence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them yf they wolde ſaye well on me but call theym flaterers fals dyſſymulours and flaterers of ſynne.</p>
               <p>Alas alas I haue heuyly dyſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded my longe lyfe that
<pb facs="tcp:173512:9"/> in all this longe tyme haue not purchaſed me. One frende to ſpeke for me had our lorde of his mooſt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple grace ordeyned me unmedyatly after my cryſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to haue dyed forth with I myght ſaye I had be borne in a gracyous houre. But wolde it pleaſe your goodnes to ſpeke for me and vnderſtande whether I ſhall haue hardynes to make a byll to the bleſſyd lady and mooſt holy vyrgyn that euer was and ſhe that dyſdayneth not nor denyeth not ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nard ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners whan they call after grace. Notwithſtandynge her chaſtyte and her pure virgynyte excelleth all other virgyns. Now good go your waye &amp; lette me wete how I ſhall ſpede for all this tyme I lyue in ſuche drede &amp; fere that me were better dye anone than lyue ony lenger in the drede that I am in. And alſo I haue ſo grete drede &amp; fere of the ryghtwyſnes of almyghty god that I am almooſt deed for fere. For reaſon drede &amp; conſcyence ſayd to me full ſhortly that the hyghe Iuge wolde not be percyall nor he wolde not be corrupte with good but he wyll mynyſter to me Iuſtyce certaynly but and he atteyneth to mynyſtre to me Iuſtyce without fauour I wyll appele to his mercyes certaynly for other reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy is ther<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none par de. Origene our bleſſyd lady helpe Thyofull / &amp; ſyr Emery how ſholde they haue done ne the moder of mercy had ben &amp; many another ſynner that her grace hath holpe. She is quene of heuen lady of the worlde and empreſſe of hell / and ſaynge to her ſone cryſt Iheſu hath dyed &amp; ſuffred ſo tourmentous a deth &amp; in her owne ſyght to her grete ſocour and mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therly compaſſyon I hope ſhe wolde be loth that theke precyous paſſyon ſholde be loſte in ony creature that her bleſſyd ſone ſuffred ſo pacyently.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:173512:9"/>
               <head>¶ The anſwere of fayth &amp; hope to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>HAue ye none acqueyntaunce wyth our brother Charyte we meruayle that ye haue not ſpoken of hym in all this tyme / for and ye were Ioyned with vs twayne your meſſage ſholde be the more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly herde manyfolde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The lamentable complaynt of the dyenge creature to fayth hope and charyte.</head>
               <p>CErtaynly I haue but lytell deled with hym. I was neuer conuerſaunt with hym &amp; that me re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>penteth now / for I fele by you twayne that he may do moche in the hygh courte. I haue more deled with ven geaunce than I haue with charyte / for I wolde haue ben auenged vpon euery man by my wyll whan the people had ſlayne my chyldren my kyn my frendes &amp; robbed &amp; ſpoyled my ſelfe certaynly I wolde haue ben a wroke ryght fayne and I had had power to my wyll but though my power were lytell certaynly I haue ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted them and wylled them to haue ben done to as they haue done to me / and wel I wote that is not the ordre of charyte. But now I hertely crye god mercy our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed lady &amp; you holy charyte of the that myn enemyes here afore god oure bleſſed lady &amp; you thre. I forgyue them all that they haue done agaynſt me / &amp; wyl not be auenged thought I myght: And I pray you holy cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryte thoughe it were longe or I were acqueynted with you be not the lother to doo for me I ſore repente me that I haue thus vnreſonably &amp; vnwyttyngely abſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me frome you &amp; hertely I crye you mercy / &amp; praye
<pb facs="tcp:173512:10"/> you of your charyte to put out of your mynde my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous foly for certaynly I ſhall neuer do ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re agayne but in euery thynge that I haue to do I ſhal deſyre your fauoure ſocour and your counſeyll and I vttery denyle &amp; deſyre vengeaunce and neuer to dele with hym no more how ſomeuer I be done to but take it in pacyence and thynke as me ought of rrght that worſe than I haue ben done to I haue deſerued to be done to / but that is not the worlde / for hym haue I ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued and pleaſed and dyſpleaſed almyghty god that is maker of al thynge and his holy begotenſone that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued was of the holy gooſt and borne was of a pure chaſte vyrgyn and dyed for our redempcyon whan I haue greuouſly offended and broken his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in all thynge knowynge that I dyde not well wherfore my peryll is the more. Nor I haue not called after the bleſſed holy gooſt graces mercy ſocour &amp; her helpe whan I haue ben in places of peryll of deedly ſynne. Nor I haue not called vpon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mooſt holy pure chaſte and mooſt excellent vyrgyn and I haue be ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght her of grace and ſhe tourned her vyſage frome me not for lacke of fayth but for me thoughe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her mooſt excellent charyte and chaſtyte muſte of very ryght ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre my ſynnes &amp; all thynge that I pleaſed the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de with I knowe well that I dyſpleaſed hym that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned me with his precyous paſſyon. And this I wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te well deſerueth a grete punyſſhemente than I haue it ſuffred and there as me lacked ſuffycyaunce and bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denes to come in the preſence of theym that I haue ſo greuouſly offended / wyll it pleaſe your goodnes Fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Hope and Charyte charytably to goo and ſtere and be meane for me to the mother of mercy and pyte
<pb facs="tcp:173512:10"/> that ſhe wolde go forime to the gloryous trynyte and take you thre with her / for well I wote the gloryous trynyte wyll no thynge denye that ſhe deſyreth they vnderſtande her perfyte charyte ſuche that euery crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture that calleth after grace ſhe hath pyte vpon theym haue they neuer ſo greuouſly offended I ſholde fall in dyſpayre &amp; I had not perfyte truſt in her grace mercy &amp; pyte. And ſo I haue grete cauſe for to haue brought my Ioly ſoule in to grete bondage and in ſuche aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte withoute remedy that it paſſeth my power to eaſe hym or helpe hym nor the grete ſpecyall truſte that I haue in that mooſt blyſſed good lady and in you holy Fayth Hope and Charyte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How the ſorowfull ſoule complayneth hym to the dyenge creature ſaynge thus.</head>
               <p>HOw nyghe haſte thou done with thy mayſter the worlde / how nyghe be ye twayne departed vnderſtandeſt thou not how vnſure he is / and at thy mooſt nede wyll fayle the / haſte thou not ſyth afore this tyme in the tymes of thy grete aduerſytees and troubles / what hath he eaſed or profyted the. Certay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne but lytell or nought / for and he haue flatered or dyſſymuled with the one daye or one houre he hathe lowred and grutched with the more than an hole yere therfore. Haſte thou not vnderſtande hym afore in all this tyme / but hanged vpon hym alwayes as longe as thou myght eſt / and yet more lenger woldeſt thou yf that thou myghteſt / but now the ſeaſon and tyme is come that he wyll departe and go frome the / and what
<pb facs="tcp:173512:11"/> dyſtreſſe that euer thou arte in lytell wyl he fauour ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour or helpe the / ſuche as thou thynkeſt be thy fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des wyll ſhewe the a fayned fououre tyll they knowe the certayne of thy ryches / and yf thou haue good they wyll cheryſſhe and fauour the for the ſeaſon / and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>playne and wayle thy deth. And yet they wolde full fayne thou were ago &amp; be ryght gladde with thy deth and whan tyme thyne eyen be cloſed / thy herynge ago thy ſpeche withdrawen &amp; may not ſpeke / than ſhalte thou ſe what thy mayſter the worlde wyll doo for the / ſeke thy cofers he wyll &amp; euery corner by the waye of lykelyhode that ony good is in / and lytell wyl they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte with to the than / &amp; lytell compaſſyon wyll they haue vpon thy poore ſoule / and they fynde lytell or nought in thy cofers what wyll they ſaye / thou thou than they wyll ſaye thou were a fole a waſter thou cou deſt not kepe / thou ſpendeſt more than than haddeſt thus wyll they ſaye by the / &amp; though they fynde moche thou ſhalte haue but lytell therof &amp; fare but lytell the better / and yf they fynde but lytell they wyll grudge with the &amp; ſaye the neuer a good worde / thynke theron by tymes &amp; be thyne owne frende / for &amp; thou can not loue thy ſelfe who wyll loue the / canſt thou loue ony creature better than thy ſelfe / &amp; yf thou do ſoo in fayth thou arte not wyſe / remembre what I ſaye now / for thou ſhalte fynde this true euery worde / and thoughe I ſpeke thus greuouſly &amp; ſtraytly vnto the meruayll not for it. I am that ſhall abyde ſuffre and endure the paynes for thy defences. Alas that euer I was cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled with the / &amp; ſo haue I cauſe to ſaye / for I ſhall be punyſſhed without fauour for thy dedes / how haſtely how ſone I can not ſaye. ¶ How vnauyſedly and how
<pb facs="tcp:173512:11"/> vnredyly thou purueyeſt for me I wote neuer how ſholde ony other creature haue compaſſyon vpon me whan thou haſte not that ſyght that thou were fyrſte fourmed a creature I haue alwayes be with the and neuer frome the and in the aege of thyne Innocencye was kepte full vertuouſly to my grete comforte. And in thy myddle age was kepte full vycyouſly and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to my grete ſorowe / and in thyne olde age lytell or noughte remembred thy wretched lyuynge. Alas Alas Alas that euer thou &amp; I were coupled togyder for the ſeaſon haſteth faſte that I muſt goo to paynes for thy myſrewle and endure payne whether it be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall or for a longe ſeaſon I wore not what remedy thy worldely frendes wyll fynde to eaſe me. I am in grete drede I trowe they wyll haue but lytell compaſſyon on me that am thy poore ſoule / but gyue theyr attendaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce for to bery the rychely and worſhypfully and make thy houſes clenly and to make thy purſe emptye and lytel compaſſyon or remembraunce wyl they haue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the and me certaynly but lette me brenne eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but yf the mercyes of hym that is almyghty by the meanes of his mooſt holy mother that pure chaſt may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den that helpeth euery ſynner that calleth after grace whan there is none other remedy. Now farwell body thou ſhalte to erth and ly and rotte and wormes ſhall ete the and I ſhall to paynes longe or elles eternally mercy bleſſed lady that bare cryſte Iheſu our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour for in none other helpe I aſſure me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The lamentable lamentacyon of the dyenge body to the ſoule.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:173512:12"/>
               <p>ALas ſely ſoule the tourmentes and the paynes of myne offences ſhall ye ſuffre I am ſoo ſory there can no tunge tell the ſorowe that I endure that haue brought you in ſuche bondage peryll daunger &amp; aduerſyte without remedy nor the hyghe and myghty mercyes of almyghty god whoſe mercyes can not be had but by the meanes of his bleſſed holy mother and yf ſhe that is ſoo chaſte ſo pure and ſoo holy wolde ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homyn the abhomynacyon of our ſynnes what ſhal I do. I haue deſyred fayth hope &amp; charyte to be my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocates to her that bare oure lorde Iheſu cryſte. And whan I am anſwered agayne ſuche anſwere as I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue I ſhall lette you wete.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How the dyenge creature complayned hym to. fayth hope and charyte ſaynge thus.</head>
               <p>OYe holy fayth hope &amp; charyte where haue ye ben ſo longe I haue lyued in grete drede how haue ye ſpedde haue ye ben with the quene of heuen lady of the worlde and empreſſe of hell that mooſt gloryous pure and chaſte vyrgyn that bare the ſone of god that ſholde redeme all mankynde / how wyll her chaſtyte her pure vyrgynyte receyue me that am a ſynner and ſuffre me to come to her preſence and putte a ſupplyca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon to her mooſt gloryous hygh and excellent prynce that I haue ſo greuouſly offended her bleſſyd ſone and her / wyll ſhe not abhorre ne dyſdayne to looke on me that am of all ſynners the mooſt horyble and abhomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable / and haue ſoo done that I can not without her mooſt haboundaunt grace fynde a meane how to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a ſyght / but I haue herde ſaye of olde antyquyte
<pb facs="tcp:173512:12"/> that ſhe is ſoo mercyable and ſo gracyous to ſynners whan they call after grace and haue holpen ſoo many ſynners that of ryght muſt haue peryſſhed neher gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce had be. But what comforte ye haue of her mooſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundaunt grace I praye you lette me wete / for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynly I lyue in grete dyſpayre / for here hath be with me ſythen that ye wente my ſoule &amp; complayned that he muſte peryſſhe eternally in my defaute and cryeth and wayleth the tyme that euer he was coupled with ſuche an vngracyous body that ſoo hath rewled hym / &amp; I can not gyue hym no comforte whithout you thre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The anſwere of fayth hope and charyte to the dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Eſemeth fayth hope &amp; charyte haue done your meſſage and fynde that prynces full gracyouſly dyſpoſed and fayth that ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth well how the gloryous trynyte choſe of one aſſente to be medyatryx and meane bytwene god and man and that her grete wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe &amp; Ioye was cauſed for oure redempcyon whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhe can not putte in oblyuyon / ano alſo the grete ſorowes not one but many that ſhe had atte her ſones paſſyon and ſawe her bleſſed and beſte beloued chylde dye ſoo tourmentouſly for the redempcyon of ſynners and he gylteles hym ſelfe in euery thynge but of his grete and mooſt ample grace mercy and charyte that he ſhewed vnto all ſynners and ſoo precyous ſo glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſoo tender was neuer man as he was for he was the veray pure / and godhede medled with her pure chaſte vyrgynyte and maydenhode and in her
<pb facs="tcp:173512:13"/> precyous body made his holy habytacyon nyne mone thes and in her ſoule eternally. And whan ſhe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode the prophecy of her grete mekenes deſyred that ſhe myghte be one of thoſe and ſympleſt ſeruaunt to her that ſholde bere the ſone of god &amp; hym that ſholde redeme all mankynde and her grete mekenes thought her ſelfe not worthy to that mooſt holy occupacyon: And therfore be of good chere for we fayth hope and charyte wyll brynge you there and not leue you tyll ye be anſwered and ſyth ye haue put your ſpecyal truſt in vs to be your aduocates and layde aperte all temporal and wordely truſte we thre wyll not fayle you / &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore putte your ſoule in comforte / and arme you with the armure of a ſure and a hole confeſſyon with a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull contrycyon purpoſynge to doo very ſatyſfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon and out of doubte / we hope ye ſhall ſpede ryght well yf it be in your herte as ye ſpeke with your mouth and elles truſt not to our frendſhyp in no wyſe but go and labour your ſupplycacyon as effectually as ye can deu yſe and be out of all dyſpayre for we fayth hope &amp; charyte wyll not leue you for the truſte that ye haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had in vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How the dyenge creature calleth after the ſoule agayne.</head>
               <p>WHere be ye dere ſoule that was with me but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te complaynynge that ye muſte to payne for a longe whyle or elles teternally and in my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faute and withoute remedy I haue ben in ſuche drede ſorowe &amp; fere for you that no thynge coude co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me
<pb facs="tcp:173512:13"/> tyll Fayth and Hope came to me and aſked me yf that I were not acqueynted with Charyte. And I haue an ſwered them ſemely that I was neuer acqueynted ne conuerſaunt with hym &amp; that me repenteth ſore / now Fayth &amp; hope haue brought me with hym and I haue humbly and lowly ſubmytted me to hym and lowly cryed hym mercy of my preſumpcyous foly promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge that I wyll neuer effende hym more denyenge all ſuche as be his enemyes and as he loueth not venge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aunce / hatered / and cruelte and promyſed hym fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully that I wyll neuer dele with them more &amp; I hope he hath pardoned me / and hath be in the company of Fayth &amp; Hope to the moder of mercy for me &amp; brought me a ryght gracyous anſwere agayne. That ſhe can not put in oblyuyon the grete Ioye worſhyp and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte that ſhe had of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone of god for the redempcyon of vs ſynners / nor the maydenly &amp; moderly compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyons that ſhe ſuffred for hym in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tymes of his mooſt precyous paynefull and bytter paſſyon &amp; that I ſhall haue herdynes to come to the preſence of that mooſt royall and emperyall prynces &amp; put a ſupplycacyon to her / and therfore be of good chere and ſuffre your pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes pacyently for thoughe it be longe I hope it ſhall not be eternally and good dere ſoule whyle ye and I be togyder or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we departe puruey in youre wyſdome ſome remedy what can be do to your eaſe &amp; I wyll be ryghte agreable therto / for whan we twayne ones be deuyded and departed fewe or none wolde haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſyon on your payne. Se ye not how the worlde low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vpon vs now euery daye and is redy to departe frome vs euery daye for lytel thynge or nought &amp; leſſe wolde they doo for vs and we twayne were departed.
<pb facs="tcp:173512:14"/> Therfore dere ſoule the remedyes that may be founde thorughe your wyſdome I praye you fynde them and I ſhall be ryght fayne to execute theym / for I am at this houre as ſory as is poſſyble ony wretche to be that I haue brought you in the peryll of daunger that ye be in &amp; as fayne wolde be to doo that ſholde eaſe you &amp; gladder than euer I was to do ony thynge that hath hurte you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How the dyenge creature putteth his ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyon to the moder of mercy Mary replete with grace prynces of reuth / mercy &amp; pyte to whome all ſynners reſorteth whan they be ſocourles.</head>
               <p>MEkely beſecheth and ſorowfully complayneth your dredfull ſupplyaunt than al my longe lyf vnto my eldeſt age haue lyued and not obeyed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes of almyghty god in noo thynge but myſuſed my lyfe in all the ſeuen deedly ſynnes / and ſynfully and ſymply haue occupyed my fyue wyttes and ſette aſyde all vertues and vſed and occupyed all vyces and ſexued the deuyll the worlde and the fleſſhe hauynge very knowlege bothe of good and euyll and knewe well that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pleaſed theym deſpyſed dyſpleaſed almyghty god. I ſpared not to dyſpleaſe god but I drede to dyſpleaſe theym and now hath a ſergeaunt of armes be with me and layde vpon me the mace of his offyce cruelly &amp; hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded me to make me redy euery houre for I ſhal not wete whan I ſhal be called to my Iugement y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> certaynte of deth he hath brought me in to the greuous infyrmyte that none erthly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyne can cure me myn enemyes be ſo grete in multy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude
<pb facs="tcp:173512:14"/> &amp; haue ouercome me &amp; all my defautes brought with them / and I wote well they wyll accuſe me my worldly frendes hath for ſake me I haue cryed &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led after them to anſwere for me and they haue anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red me ryght ſtraytly &amp; vnfrendly that they neyther dare ne can ne wyll not anſwere for me nor excuſe me And ſhortly they be departed away from my good au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell fyrſte reaſon drede and conſcyence and my fyue wyttes haſteth them faſte from me warde and leueth me deſtytute and all one / and where to haue ſocourne helpe I wote not but as it fortuneth me in good tyme may I ſaye I mette me with Fayth Hope &amp; Charyte and they haue promyſed me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wyll ſpeke to your mooſt excellent benygne grace and mercy for me and ſo I truſte they haue for certayne of your mooſt pure chaſte vyrgynyte &amp; vnwemmed maydenhode I was neuer in thought. And I haue hoped &amp; truſted to your mercyes alwaye I haue herde ſaye that ye be mother of orphans and I wys I am a very orphan fatherles and motherles / ye be dyſſolat comforte and ſocour to all tho that be deſtytute dyſſolate and ſocourles I wys lady that am I for I haue neyther ſocoure helpe nor conforte of no creature but onely the truſt that I haue in your benygne grace ye be guyde vnto them that be out of the waye and ſeke the meanes for to come in to the ryght waye. A bleſſed lady I haue be ſo longe out of the waye that I fere and drede for too call to you for grace / but as Fayth Hope and Charyte haue put me in comforte how loth ye be to ſee your bleſſed ſones precyous and bytter paſſyon loſte in my creature and they haue gyuen me hardynes for to call vpon your mooſt noble and benygne grace. And ſoo good bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:173512:15"/> lady with humble dredfull &amp; ſorowfull herte &amp; mynde I beſeche your mooſt benygne grace mercy and pyte to ſet me in the ryght way of ſaluacyon and make me one of the partyners of youre bleſſed ſones precyous paſſyon &amp; of your maydenly &amp; motherly compaſſyons &amp; as ye be come borowe for Mary Egypcyan to your bleſſed ſone. So good lady be my borowe that I ſhall neuer frome hens forth wylfully offende your bleſſed ſone nor you but ſore repente that euer I ſawe / herde or dyde ony thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges that hath dyſpleaſed your bleſſed ſone or you beynge in wyll neuer to retourne to ſynne and wretchednes agayne but rather to dye than wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to doo ony thynge that ſholde dyſpleaſe my lorde cryſt Iheſu or you. Now prynces excellent &amp; excelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of myght &amp; worthynes al creatures as in dygnyte my herte lady my worldly chefe goodes pray your ſone to haue mercy vpon me ſyth in all my greteſt myſchefe to your grace I flee I can no ferder refute to fynde ony conſolacyon / &amp; ſyth my hope and truſte is onely ſet in you be ye my refuge now in this grete trybulacyon co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer my ſynfull ſowle with the mantyll of your mercy es and ſet your ſones precyous paſſyon bytwyne me and eternall dampnacyon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The ſupplycacyon of our lady to our lorde Iheſu her ſone for the ſeke creature.</head>
               <p>O Iheſu my lorde my god mooſt bleſſed ſone in whome is all plente of grace &amp; of vnthoughted mercye to &amp; for al ſynners that in ſted faſt fayth and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured hope deuoutly call vnto you for helpe and grace &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſechynge mercy &amp; foryeuenes of theyr myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fawtes
<pb facs="tcp:173512:15"/> and offences to you I come as a ſolyciter and a beſecher for this ſeke creature whiche with humble and ſorowfull and a contryte herte ſueth contynually for your grace and pardon that it myght lyke you to in clyne you of your vnyte pyte to his requeſtes and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>playntes and graciouſly to conſyder his nedes and cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes he is ſore abaſſhed and dyſcomfyted in hym ſelfe &amp; as who ſayth vtterly confounded conſyderynge his greuous and depe ſynnes by the whiche he hath prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked your wrath and indygnacyon by the whiche alſo he is ſore encombred and ſtandeth in grete daunger of his enemy and namely he fereth hym of your dredfull Iugement for well he woteth yf ye do hym Iuſtyce he is but loſte for euer / yet for all this he dyſpayreth not of your mercy for he is in good opynyon and truſteth to reioyſe your pardone and to be reconſyled to grace wherupon he ſueth contynually vnto you as he maye and dare / for he knoweth hym ſelfe ſo depely charged in ſynne &amp; ſoo ferre elonged for ſynne grace by ſynne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he thynketh hym ſelfe vnworthy to approche to offre his owne prayer / therfore he ſueth by meanes and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyally by me to whome he calleth inportunely with py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous &amp; waylynge voyce &amp; ſeketh not but contynueth to ſobbynge &amp; wepynge ſoo lamentably that my herte erneth to here / and certes I can not me no lenger con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne but to inſtant his prayers and to put me in your grace for hym for he calleth me the mother of mercye for encheſon that I bare you with be the very fountay nes and welles of mercy and haue it of vnſeuerall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete to be mercyable to all ſynners / &amp; for this he cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengeth me in maner as though I ſholde owe of dute to enterparte my labours and prayers in this behalfe
<pb facs="tcp:173512:16"/> with hym and for hym / and to ſue for the haſty ſpede of his reconſylacyon and that he letteth not to put me in mynde that I was ordeyned of god to be meane by twene hym and man / &amp; certes I alowe wel his mynde therin / for true it is that I ought ſoo to be that lyke wyſe that ye my dere lorde and ſone deſcended frome heuen to erth by me and be came pertyner of mannes nature by me. Soo all ſynners that be not in eſtate of grace ſholde be reconſyled and reſtored to grace by me and be made pertyners of your Ioye by me. ¶ This is well ſygnyfyed in the fygure of aarons rode whiche bare a floure myraculouſly as ſcrypture wytneſſeth. The whiche rode ſygnyfyeth me lyke as the floure be tokeneth you / for as a rode groweth dyrectly upwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and is the ſtreyght meane bytwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rode and the floure / and he that wyll clyne togyder the floure muſt aſcende by the rode or elles bowe the rode &amp; cauſe the floure to ſtoupe / ſo he that wylleth to ryſe frome ſynne muſt ryſe by me / and he that wyll acclyne your grace and reioyſe your pardon muſt bowe me by prayer that I may cauſe you to ſtoupe that is to ſaye too inclyne to here prayer and requeſtes and to let dyſcende your bemes of grace to theym. ¶ Lo thus my dere ſone and lorde it is open and euydent that I am ordeyned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſyle man and that / it is in maner my dewte and offyce ſo to doo / wherfore ſyth this ſeke creature thus contynually and vnfatygably cryeth to me with py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and doulfull complaynt and requyreth me ſoo ſtraytly that I can not ſeas to put me in endure for hym and enterparte my labours with hym for hym / and certes it is not onely for his inportune ſuyte and prayer but alſo for other conſyderacyons reſonable &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:173512:16"/> charytable that moueth me to tender and inſtant his cauſes / one is that he is alyed to me ryght nye by ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall cognacyon for bothe we haue one fader that is god whiche is your fader by creacyon and one moder the chirche whiche is our moder by regeneracion thus is he my broder and I his ſyſter and now my lorde me ſemeth ryght vnſyttynge me beynge a quene to ſe my brother a pryſoner I at lyberte and he in thraldome I in blyſſe and he in tourment / wherfore I am conſtray ned as who ſayth by nature to ſue for his delyuerynge and reconſylynge &amp; this is one of the conſyderacyons that reſonably moueth me to ſue for his pardon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The ſeconde conſyderacyon.</head>
               <p>ANother is that ſyth it lyked you of your grete bounte and ineſtymable charyte for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reconſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of man to take of me your handmayden fleſſhe and blode and bone and the ſayd fleſſhe and bloode to offre in ſacrefyce for redempcyon of me and this &amp; all other whome it hath and ſhall lyke you to call to your fayth me ſemeth I ought not / for as moche as in me lyeth to ſee that thynge myſcarye whiche you haue ſoo precyouſly redemed &amp; bought as derely as ye bought me and with the ſame fleſſhe and blode that ye toke of me your humble creature and handmayden.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The thyrde conderacyon.</head>
               <p>AN other is this I and euery your other creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res before youre partye bowed to ſue meanes to honoure to worſhyppe to gloryfye you in that we
<pb facs="tcp:173512:17"/> can or may / but ſo it is that in Iuſtyfyenge of this ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner grete honoure and glory ſhal be to you and to your ſayntes for your ſcrypture ſayth. Gaudiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt angelis dei ſuper vno peccatore penitenciam agenti. That is to ſaye Ioye and gladnes is to your aungelles the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſyon of one ſynner contryte &amp; penytent and in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place your ſcrypture ſayth. Magis gaudium eſt ſuper peccatore penitenciam agenti quaui ſuper nona ginta nomen iuſtis. That is to ſaye and to ſygnyfye that more Ioye and honour is to god in reconſylynge a ſynner that is in full and aſſured purpoſe to perſeuer in grace than in grete multytude of other ryghtwys that neuer offended. ¶ Wherfore my lorde as I am bounde to honour and gloryfye you ſo am I bounde in maner to make inſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for reconſylynge of this your creature in the whiche thynge ye ſhal be gretely honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red and gloryfyed &amp; theſe be the thynges that moueth me to inſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſolycyt his cauſes and to ſubmytte me for hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The fourth conſyderacyon.</head>
               <p>FOrthermore I ſe in hym grete abylyte and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelyhode to ſe that creature that may ſerue you honoure and gloryfye you for he is entyerly dyſpleaſed with hym ſelfe that he hath ſoo greuouſly ſynned and offended your grace and he is ryght heuy and contryte therfore and he remembreth hym many ſythes of his olde ſynnes not as delytynge ne hauynge pleaſure in theym but to his ſhame and grete remors and he hath theym in perfyte hatred in ſo moche that he wolde not offende agayne in the leeſt of theym for all the worlde
<pb facs="tcp:173512:17"/> he hathe faſtened his entente and purpoſe to be here after all of other demeanynge thrugh your helpe and grace and he wyll gladly do penaunce for that he hath treſpaſſed and he lowly ſubmytteth hym ſelfe to the correccyon of youre chirche and wylfully aſſenteth to paye the fynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſuffre the penaunce atttaxed by your chirche and to do ſatyffaccion as is for his freylte poſſyble. And where as he ſayth hym ſelfe not of aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte ne power to do ſatyſfaccyon as hym oweth in that behalfe he putteth hym ſelfe holy in your grace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytteth hym to your grete mercy and to the meryte of your paſſyon whiche counteruayleth and preuayleth all the penaunce and ſatyſfaccyon that myght be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble for to be done by all the worlde from Adam tyll to the laſte creature that ſhall be borne. ¶ And he py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly cryeth to me and beſecheth me to enterpoſe my merytes betwene your Iugement and hym &amp; to offre in ſacryfyce for hym the ſobbynge and ſyghynges the ſorowfull and lamentable terys that I wepte for you in your tender age and chyldhode whan Symeon pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phecyed to me your paſſyon / and whan I had loſt you in Iheruſalem and the ſorowes that I ſuffred for you in tyme of your paynefull and greuous paſſyon whan the ſwerde of ſorowe peryſſhed my herte. And certes I am ryght wyll content and gladde ſo to do. And I beſeche you ſoo to accepte my merytes for his / as he goodly deſyreth and to ſet my ſorowes &amp; teres of pyte in place of his penaunce and contrycyon. ¶ Forther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more it myght lyke you to conſyder the grete labour &amp; beſynes of Fayth Hope and Charyte and namely for charyte whiche ſueth for hym contynually and neuer is ydell but beſy to labour for hym / and ſhe cleueth and
<pb facs="tcp:173512:18"/> calleth for me for hym inceſſauntly to ſe the expeccyon of his cauſes / and ſhe vndertaketh for his aberynge &amp; well ye wote that her deſyre and prayer maye not be voyde ne fruſtratte but ſhe muſt be gracyouſly herde in all her goodly requeſtes and deſyres. She hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo receyued fayth and hope on her partye for this ſeke creature and hath profeſſed to kepe your fayth inuyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably and hope hath put hym in ful aſſuraunce of your mercy / for thoughe it ſoo be that he ſe not in hym ſelfe wherof he may truſte to reioyſe your pardon / yet ſhe ſheweth hym that in you is ſoo greate promptues of mercy and contynuall coſtome that you be wonte and vſed alwaye to forgyue and haue of naturall proprete for to be mercyable to all ſynners that it maketh hym bolde to faſten the anker of his hope in you &amp; truſteth fynally to make a vyage in the porte of your mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The concluſyon of our ladyes ſupplycacyon.</head>
               <p>NOw my lorde ſyth all the good abylytes &amp; dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſico<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns vnto grace be in this creature by your ſuffraunce / there is no more to doo but that ye let deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende your grace to the veſſell ſo dyſpoſed and that you voucheſaufe to ſuffre hym reioyſe your pardon and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conſyle hym to your chirche and make hym a membre therof the ſoner and ſpedlyer for this my prayer and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>queſt. I you beſeche my mooſt dere lorde and ſone who me it hathe lyked you alwaye to here gracyouſly and neuer ſuffre to departe boteles of petycyon for whiche be to you and to your mooſt honourably and drad fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the holy gooſt your egall pere euerlaſtynge Ioye honour and glory. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:18"/>
            <trailer>¶ Here endeth a lytell treatyſe of the dyenge creature</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Enprynted at London in Fleteſtrete at the ſygne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne by wynkyn de worde. Anno dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i. M. CCCCC. vii.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>Sis humilis</q>
                  <q>Victus ſum</q>
                  <q>Superbos punio</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:19"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Wynkyn de Worde's device</figDesc>
                  <p>Wynkyn de Worde</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:21"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173512:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
